玄黄端现 太极混沌如鸡蛋
In the beginning there was darkness and then
随着轰的一声
bang giving birth to an endless expanding existence
诞生了无限膨胀的时间 空间和物质
of time, space and matter.
现在所见超乎我们的想象
Now see further that we've ever imagined
超越了客观认知极限
beyond the limits of our existence
那地方我们称之为"宇宙"
in a place we call "the universe".
我们那无限的宇宙充满着怪异 暴戾
Our infinite universe is brimming with strange, violent
以及潜在的生命传输现象
and potentially life-transporting phenomena.
想象一下宇宙的门户
Imagine cosmic portals
在那里物体会消失 被弹出
where objects could disappear, be ejected
或者泄漏到时空中的一些其它的地方
or escape to some other place in space or time.
它们是去绝大多数湮没之地的入场券
They are tickets to oblivion for the most part.
你或者在通过虫洞传送到宇宙的另一部分去时
Either you get shredded in a black hole you get transported
被黑洞碾得粉碎
to another part of the universe in a wormhole, or you get
或者被白洞的喷射物所毁灭
obliterated by the gusher of the white hole.
飞行去宇宙的弯曲的那头
Blast off to the warp side of the universe
科学家们为了搜索黑洞
as scientists search for black holes
白洞和虫洞
white holes and wormholes.
它们是没有意义的幻想… 还是一个科学事实呢？
Are they frivolous fantasies... or a science fact?
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://cmct.cc
影片压制:春树  字幕来源:五羊皮  调校:御雪寒狼  招募Q号:76846146
[历史频道] 第二季 第二集 宇宙中的洞
[History Channel] The UniverseⅡ 02of19 Cosmic.Holes
宇宙是一个一切皆有可能的聚宝盆
The universe is a cosmic cornucopia of endless possibilities.
设想穿梭往返到宇宙中的任何一个地方
Imagine a shuttle service to anywhere in the cosmos.
不是登上未来的宇宙飞船
It's not aboard a futuristic spaceship;
而是乘坐银河交通工具通过虫洞
it's a galactic ride through a wormhole...
一种理论上的通道
a theoretical tunnel.
提供了通过时空的捷径
providing shortcuts through space and time.
虫洞有点象城市中的地铁系统
Wormholes are a little bit like a subway system that you might use in the city
你进入一个洞口
where you're going into a hole
经过一个隧道然后在
you go through a tunnel and then you come out
另外一头的洞口出来
at the other end through another hole
这样你就穿越了城市 同样也可能
and then you've traveled through the city. Same thing would be possible
通过虫洞在宇宙间两个不同地点之间进行旅行
in a wormhole to travel between different points in the universe.
物理学家克利福德·约翰逊
Physicist Clifford Johnson
已经对虫洞的可能性进行过深思
has contemplated the possibility of wormholes.
虫洞与地铁之间的区别
The difference between a wormhole and a subway system
在于你通过虫洞旅行的行程
is that you're using the wormhole
要比你在平常的
to travel a greater distance than you would
空间里旅行大得多
if you were traveling in ordinary space.
理论上虫洞是连接出入口的
In theory a wormhole has a throat
咽喉称做"嘴巴"
connected to an entrance and exit called "mouths"
嘴巴位于空间的各个部位
located in different parts of space.
虫洞很有吸引力
A wormhole is appealing because
因为我们受光速的限制无法超过光速到达仙女星座
we're limited by the speed of light. We can't get to the Andromeda galaxy
即使达到光速也需要60万年才能到达
in less than something like 600,000 years even moving at the speed of light.
我一直感到疑惑
I keep wondering if
天文学的下一个伟大的发现究竟是不是虫洞
the really next big discovery in astronomy could be a wormhole.
现在只是因为它们引起了象我这样的人的兴趣
Not just because they're fun for people like me
而不是因为
but because
它们可以将我们带到某些我们貌似无法用其他途径抵达的地方
they could take us to some place that we can't plausibly ever get any other way.
格里高里·本福德已经在构思外层空间的科幻小说了
Gregory Benford has pondered the science and fiction of outer space.
身兼物理学家和30多部科幻小说的作家
As both a physicist and author of over 30 sci-fi novels
本福德已经目睹了科幻成真
Benford has witnessed fantastical theories become a reality.
我们中许多人都想知道
A lot of us would like to know if wormholes
虫洞是真的存在？或者只是建立在
really exist or whether they're just another mathematical construct
爱因斯坦天赋上的又一个数学模型呢？
thought up by Einstein the genius.
爱因斯坦的广义相对论
Albert Einstein's general relativity laws
考虑到了虫洞的存在
allows for the existence of wormholes.
1930年爱因斯坦和他的同事纳森·罗森
In 1930 Einstein and his colleague Nathan Rosen
计算出了这些星系间管道中的一个数学模型
calculated the mathematics of one of these intergalactic pipelines.
也就是大家熟知的"爱因斯坦—罗森桥"
It became known as the "Einstein-Rosen bridge."
虫洞是爱因斯坦方程式的一个解答
The wormhole is a solution of Einstein's equations for
这是广义相对论论述引力作用的方程式
general relativity telling us how gravity works.
他们假设
They're hypothetical
他们这样做是为了将时空的各个部分连接起来
and what they do is they connect different parts of space and time.
爱因斯坦—罗森的数学虫洞
The Einstein-Rosen mathematical wormhole
是受黑洞的研究启发的
arose from studying black holes.
黑洞是引力极其强烈的空间中的一个区域
A black hole is a region in space of extremely strong gravity.
引力强烈到
The gravity is so strong
它附近的物体没有任何办法
that there is no way for objects that get too near
挣脱它的引力束缚
to break away from its gravitational pull.
任何东西一旦遭遇到黑洞都无法逃逸
Nothing can escape a close encounter with a black hole
甚至光也同样逃不出来
not even light.
这个倒置的喷泉是个视觉模型
This inverted fountain serves as a visual analogy
来看一下围绕着黑洞究竟发生了什么
to what's going on around a black hole.
在这个黑洞的范围内的底部
At the bottom is the area inside the event horizon
不停地流进去的水
And the water falling into it
类似于可能流进黑洞的气体
is analogous to gas that might fall into a black hole;
你把自己想象成一条在里面游泳的鱼
Imagine yourself being a fish swimming around this region.
一旦你掉进这中央
Once you get down inside this central portion
你就此消失在这里而无法返回了
you're past the point of no return.
但是爱因斯坦从未打算将虫洞
But Einstein never intended his wormhole
作为太空旅行的工具
as a tool for space travel.
他的虫洞只是在某个时间瞬间所创造的理论
His wormhole is theoretically created at some moment of time.
它短暂打开
It opens up briefly
然后就掐断
then pinches off.
任何企图通过的东西
Anything that tries to pass through it
都将在它的挤压下粉身碎骨
will get crushed when it squeezes apart.
在你的方程式和研究中所记录到的典型的虫洞
A typical wormhole that you write down
是不稳定的它会在难以想象的短时间内消失
in your equations and study is unstable. It will vanish in an incredibly short time.
因此你需要一些手段来让它保持开放
So what you need is some means of holding it open.
在爱因斯坦的虫洞被确定没有规则之后
After Einstein's wormhole was determined unstable
上世纪60年代
in the 1960s
在这方面的概念便少有研究
little research was done on the concept.
后来科幻电影
Then the sci-fi film "contact"
在90年代后期放映
was released in the late 1990s.
是根据著名天文学家卡尔·萨根的原著拍摄的
Based on the book by renowned astronomer Carl Sagan
它提出虫洞
it proposed that a wormhole
可以用来进行太空旅行
could be used for space travel.
小说及后来的电影
The book "contact" and then subsequently the movie
让大家通过
was a nice place in fiction
虚构很好地认识到了虫洞的概念
that was accessible to everyone where you can see the idea of a wormhole.
因此这是个很好的途径
So it was a nice way of
让人们再一次对那个概念引起兴趣
getting people interested in that idea all over again.
这是种非常不着边际的概念
This was kind of a very far-fetched idea
甚至连许多物理学家都没有认真考虑过
that wasn't even considered very seriously by many physicists
直至卡尔·萨根决定写这本书
Until Carl Sagan decided to write this book
试图让它尽可能地符合实际
and try to make it as realistic as possible.
打那时起理论物理着手研究
And since that time theoretical physicists studying
爱因斯坦的广义相对论
Einstein's general theory of relativity
考虑到了通过虫洞进行旅行
have considered travel through wormholes.
科学家开始研究
Scientists began to investigate
是否可能存在一种
whether there might be a type of wormhole
不同于爱因斯坦所说的虫洞
different from Einstein's
而是可通过的
that is traversible.
我们从来没有拒绝以前的问题
We've never seen negative matter before.
将会存在反万有引力的东西…
It would have anti-gravitational properties...
但是有一天 一旦我们找到了反物质
But one day, if we ever find negative matter,
或许就找到了虫洞稳定的关键
perhaps that's the key to stabilize the wormhole.
可通过的虫洞概念
The idea of a traversible wormhole
让科幻小说爱好者入了迷
captivated science fiction enthusiasts.
这也再次激发了
It also reinvigorated the serious study
科学界对虫洞的认真研究
of wormholes within the science community.
这个可通过的虫洞制造了不小的轰动
This transversible wormhole created quite a sensation
因为也许完全有可能
'cause perhaps it is physically possible
有一天能创建一个地铁系统去另外一个银河系
to one day build a subway system to another galaxy.
"虫洞"这个名称来自苹果的比喻
The term "wormhole" came from an analogy with an apple. You want to get
你想从苹果的一处到另外一处
from one part of the apple to another part.
如果你是条蠕虫就能咬出一条通道进入苹果内部
If you're a worm you can eat your way down into the body of the apple
产生一条小隧道 还有其它更短的路径
and make a little tunnel and come out the other way and it's shorter.
然而不同于蠕虫在这个苹果里活动 对于我们宇宙间的虫洞来说
But unlike a worm moving here on this apple, for a wormhole in our universe,
我们可能无法知道虫洞另一端所存在的危险
we might not know what dangers lie at the other end of the wormhole.
虫洞的另一端可能连接着
The other end of a wormhole could be connected
宇宙非常危险的地方
to a very dangerous part of the universe
具有各种奇特的现象
with all sorts of exotic phenomena.
甚至可能会是一颗恒星的核
It might even be in the core of a star.
如果我们真的找到一个虫洞 如果它距离我们足够的近
If we ever find a wormhole, and if it's close enough for us to reach,
几乎可以肯定 我们会首先发射自动探测器去通过
almost certainly we'll first send automated probes through
指引它们返回 甚至可能将它们连在电缆上
and direct them to come back, maybe even put them on a cable,
以防某些危险的情况危害它们而无法返回
in case something nasty happens to them and they can't return.
物理学家们无论如何都无法知道
Physicists do not know of any way
宇宙间可能天生就存在着虫洞
that a wormhole might arise naturally in our universe.
但是他们能创造出人造的虫洞吗？
But can they be made artificially?
物理学家思考可能让你创建
One possibility that physicists speculated about
虫洞的一种可能性
that might allow you to construct wormholes,
是它们突然出现在被认为是
would be to blow them up from what's considered to be
实际上可能包含了弯弯曲曲存在的
the fabric of space-time that might actually contain
细小虫洞的时空结构中
tiny wormholes sieving in and out of existence
这是量子力学定律决定的
due to the laws of quantum mechanics.
科学家提出或许"可通过的虫洞"
Scientists proposed that perhaps traversible wormholes
会塑造出量子泡沫:
could be sculpted out of quantum foam:
亚原子的泡沫状结构
a subatomic bubble-like structure
可能存在于宇宙的各个地方
that might exist everywhere in the universe
其长度要比原子核小10万亿亿倍
on length scales a billion trillion times smaller than the nucleus of an atom.
那么你如何来实现呢？原则上
That's how you do it. In principle it's
使用我们所掌握的所有科技是难以实现的
completely unfeasible using any technology that we know of
然而它至少是你可以关注的
but it's at least something you might consider.
如果有虫洞设计出来 或位于空间
If one could be engineered or located in space,
科学家就会考虑虫洞的其它可能发生的情况
scientists contemplated other possibilities for a wormhole.
它能将星系游客送到各个时间点
Could it transport galactic vacationers to different points in time,
以及各个空间去吗？
as well as different places in space?
为了实际上创造一个时光机器
To actually create a time machine
或虫洞机器带我们去遥远的星系
or a wormhole machine, that would take us to a distant galaxy,
你就必须具备发达文明的物理学
you would have to have the physics of an advanced civilization.
或许是我们这代人数百万年后的文明
A civilization perhaps millions of years beyond ours.
时光机器
Time machines
迷惑电影观众
have mystified movie audiences
已经超过50个年头了
for over 50 years.
先生们
Gentlemen
我来谈论穿过时光的旅行
I am talking about traveling through time
在这创造的机器里实现伟大的目标
in a machine constructed for that very purpose.
然而虫洞可以用来进行这样的旅行吗？
But could a wormhole be used for such travel?
虫洞可以做到可能走几步就到达
The wormhole may lead to things like
另外一个星系这样的事情
being able to go to another galaxy by walking five feet
通过虫洞 甚至还能进入另外一个时间
through a wormhole, or even going to another time.
但是虫洞作为时光机器会引起令人不安的问题
But wormholes as time machines pose unsettling questions.
在遥远的将来世人可以回到过去
In the distant future will earthlings be able to travel to the past
或许还能改写历史吗？
and perhaps change history?
这些今天看来很不现实的科学概念
Scientific ideas considered far-fetched today,
可能有朝一日会被接受
could one day become as acceptable
犹如接受地球是圆的那样的事实
as the fact that Earth is round.
物理定律可能会承认虫洞的存在
The laws of physics may allow for the existence of wormholes:
隧道提供了捷径来通过空间
tunnels providing shortcuts through space
以及时间
as well as time.
那么这些理论上的宇宙地铁系统
So could these cosmic subway systems
能设计成时光机器吗？
theoretically be engineered into time machines?
爱因斯坦的广义相对论揭示了
Einstein's General Relativity laws reveal
时光旅行进入未来是可能的
that time travel into the future is possible.
广义相对论表明所感受的时间是不同的
They show that time is perceived differently
有赖于物体所处的宇宙中的位置和运动方式
depending on where one is in the universe and how one moves.
物体在接近光速运动时
Objects moving at close to the speed of light,
岁月的流失要比静止的物体来得慢
age slower than static objects.
而物体靠近引力体
And objects near a gravitating body
岁月的流失要比远离引力体来得慢
age more slowly than objects farther away.
时钟的运转在不同的引力场里的速度是不同的
Clocks run at different rates in different gravitational fields.
引力场的强度越大
The stronger the gravitational field,
时间的流失越慢
the more slowly time passes
相对那些在外太空的人
relative to someone out in space
那里不存在引力场
where there's no gravitational field.
而在地球上站在其表面
On Earth, here on the surface,
我们的时钟就要比处于高空的时钟走得慢一些
our clocks run slightly more slowly than clocks high up in the sky.
这方面有个例子
So an example of this is that the clocks
卫星上的GPS系统中的时钟
in the GPS system of satellites,
就要比地球上的时钟走得稍微快一点
run a little bit more quickly than the clocks here on Earth.
因为它们处在弱一点的引力场里
Because they're in a weaker gravitational field.
科学家和工程师们开发GPS系统
And the scientists and engineers developing the GPS system,
就必须考虑到那里的时钟不同的运行速度
had to take into account the different rate at which clocks run.
如果他们做得不够准确
If they hadn't done that correctly,
那么你的GPS系统就无法工作
then your GPS system wouldn't work.
如果你从洛杉矶到纽约去旅行
If you were taking a trip from Los Angeles to New York,
结果却到了马萨诸塞州的某个地方了
you'd end up somewhere in Massachusetts.
向前的时光旅行已经通过高精度的原子钟得到了验证
Forward time travel has been tested using highly-precise atomic clocks.
科学家将一只钟放在地面上
Scientists have placed one clock on the ground
另一只放在地球上空飞行的火箭上
and another in a rocket flying high above the Earth.
通过无线电信号来对比火箭与地面上的钟
The two were compared using radio signals between rocket and ground.
火箭上的钟要走快一些
The clock on the rocket ticked faster.
在地面上我的时钟要走得慢一些
Here on Earth, my clock is running more slowly
相对远离地球的飞船上的人们
compared to someone in a rocket ship somewhere further away from Earth.
因此他们的时钟运转得快一些他们进入未来要快一些
So their clock is moving more quickly. They're going to the future faster.
物理学家研究了虫洞
Physicists have studied whether wormholes could provide travel
不光可以进入未来
not only to the future,
还能回到过去
but also to the past.
如果有个虫洞 一个口子靠近地球
If there was a wormhole with one mouth near Earth
另外一头在我们的银河系的中央
and the other in the center of our galaxy
相对于外面的宇宙 时光流失的速度
the rate of flow of time will be different at the one mouth
在"嘴"两头是不一样的
than at the other when compared to the external universe,
但是通过虫洞直接观察时
but when looking directly through the wormhole
表现出来的时间流失是一样的
the rate of flow of time appears to be the same.
它们相对的时间速度
This difference in their relative ticking rates
因为外部观察和进入虫洞内部观察的不同
as viewed externally versus viewed through the wormhole
会把虫洞转换成时光机器
would convert the wormhole into a time machine.
那就意味着通过进入虫洞
What that means is that by entering a wormhole
你就能现在从这里离开而在数百年甚至数千年前
you could leave here today and come out the other end of the wormhole
在虫洞的另外一头出来
hundreds or thousands of years earlier.
虫洞可以导致
The wormhole may lead to
能够去另外一个星系
things like being able to go to another galaxy...
甚至到达另外一个时间点之类的情况
or even going to another time.
有可能你能够利用某些虫洞
It's possible you can use a wormhole of a certain kind
居然能够把信息传送回过去或把人送回过去
to actually transport information backward in time or people backward in time.
但是时光倒流引发了令人不安的悖论
But backward time travel raises disturbing paradoxes.
人们真的能够回到过去改变历史吗？
Could one actually voyage to the past and change history?
时光倒流带来的问题之一是会产生各种悖论
One of the problems with traveling backwards in time is that it produces
其中最著名的就是祖父悖论
various paradoxes, the most famous of this is the grandfather paradox.
它说如果我有部时光机器能将我带回过去
It says that if i have a time machine that could go back in time
我就能杀死自己的祖父
and i could kill my grandfather
那么就永远没有我的父亲了
who would then never have had my father,
也就永远没有我了 我就永远到不了人世
who would never have had me I would never have been born.
那就意味着 从一开始你永远不可能回到过去
So that means you would never have been able to go back into the past in the first place.
或者可以这么说 你回到过去
Or let's say you go backwards in time
遇到你出生前的年轻时的母亲
and meet your teenage mother before you're born,
然后你那年轻的母亲与你坠入情海
and then your teenage mother falls in love with you
那么你怎么能够生出来呢？
then how can you be born
只要当时你那年轻的母亲一脚踢开你的父亲
if your teenager mother spurned your father
而与你热恋了呢？
and fell in love with you instead?
实际上问题很大
The practical problems are enormous.
但是有一天如果有人敲你的门
But one day, if somebody knocks on your door
自称是你的曾曾曾曾曾曾孙女
and claims to be your great great great great great great great granddaughter
是从未来来到这里
someone from the future going backwards in time
来见她杰出的祖先的话
to meet her illustrious ancestor
别把她拒之门外:或许在将来我们的后代
don't slam the door: perhaps in the future our descendants
将有可能进行时光旅行 或许有那么一天
will have the possibility of time travel and perhaps one day
他们可能会来敲你的门的
they may come knocking on your door.
倒回时光旅行引发了无数的
Backward time travel has ignited a myriad
科幻小说的情节
of science fiction scenarios.
如果机器做你所说的它能够做的事情的话
If that machine can do what you say it can
乔治 在它消灭你之前摧毁它
destroy it, George before it destroys you.
假如物理定律允许虫洞…
If the laws of physics permit wormholes...
那么这些定律又是如何处理改变历史的危险的呢？
then how can those laws deal with the danger of changing history?
一种可能性是物理定律
One possibility is that the laws of physics
允许你去…
allow you to do...
时光倒回旅行 只要它导致的是…
backward time travel as long as it leads to...
首尾一致的宇宙 这在一定意义上
a self-consistent universe that in some sense the history is not
历史是不会改变的 你无法回去改变什么的
changeable you can't go backwards and change things
这在事件的起始点就将阻止你
which would stop you from having been created in the first place
那个祖父悖论就是个例子
for example in the grandfather paradox.
目前通过虫洞前行或倒退的时光旅行
For now forward or backward time travel through a wormhole
依然一团疑问
remains in question.
一些科学家认为任何创造虫洞时光机器的企图
And some scientists think that any attempt to create a wormhole time machine
都可能摧毁虫洞
may destroy the wormhole.
实际上你一旦企图利用虫洞进入时光机器
What actually happens when you try and make that wormhole into a time machine
只要把不同的时间连接起来
is that as soon as it starts connecting different times
你就会受到大量十分强烈的辐射
you get a pile up of radiation so intense
它将摧毁整个虫洞
that it destroys the entire wormhole
这样就会阻止你利用虫洞进入时光机器
thus stopping you from making that wormhole into a time machine.
这似乎是个信号 可能这是自然规律
There seems to be a sign that maybe this is the way nature
本身利用物理定律来避免可能产生的悖论
protects itself using the laws of physics from ever producing paradoxes
以及时光机器似乎会引发的怪异的情况
and strange things that time machines seem to suggest.
虫洞旅行实在是有点玄乎
Wormhole travel is really iffy
因为关于虫洞 你已经了解了很多
because you have to know a lot about the wormhole
因此它不会干让人不快的事情的 比如
so that it doesn't do unpleasant things like for example
突然把你变成一个大的气球
turn you into a big ball of gas all of a sudden,
因为维持虫洞的万有引力
because the gravitational stresses that support the wormhole...
貌似很强的
are plausibly quite strong.
虫洞的概念…
The idea of a wormhole...
并不是我们可以视若无睹认为"不可能的东西"
is not something that we can point to and say "that's impossible."
它会很荒谬地宣称:"我们不可能那么做的"
It would be absurd to say "we can't do that ever"
因为涉及的能力 能量
because we're dealing with powers energies
及知识已经超出了我们目前的范畴
and knowledge that are outside of our current domain.
比如虫洞存在另外一个现象
Like a wormhole there's another phenomenon
从来没有被发现
that has never been discovered.
然而爱因斯坦的广义相对论
But Einstein's general relativity laws
承认它的存在
allow for its existence.
它被称之为"白洞"
It's called a "white hole."
黑洞是东西掉进去就消失的物体
Well a black hole is an object into which things are falling and disappearing,
有点像排水口 而白洞刚好相反东西被抛出来
rather like a sinkhole. A white hole is doing the opposite things are coming out.
东西被抛出来有点象喷泉
Things are coming out rather like a fountain.
白洞象独角兽
A white hole is like the unicorn:
一种怪异的动物 以前从来没见过
an exotic animal that's never been seen before.
白洞和黑洞非常相似 就是动作刚好相反
A white hole is very similar to a black hole except it runs backwards.
有点象录像带倒带
Think of running the videotape backwards.
掉进其范围内的物质永远被抛出来
Instead of matter falling into the event horizon never to come out
而不象黑洞 物质被吸进去
matter falls out of a black hole.
因此刚好是把黑洞颠倒了过来
So it's the opposite a time reversed black hole.
我们已经了解到黑洞
Black holes as we know have now been understood to be
存在于我们的宇宙间
out there in our universe
因此你可能会怀疑白洞是否也同样如此呢
and so you might wonder whether the same thing is true about white holes as well.
比如类星体被首次发现时
For example quasars when they were first discovered
就被认为可能是白洞
were thought to be maybe white holes.
为什么呢？因为它们产生大量的能量
Why? Because they seem to be producing a huge amount of energy.
现在我们知道这并不是事实
We now know that that's not the case.
类星体其实是由黑洞驱动的
Quasars are actually powered by black holes.
有些学派声称白洞可能存在于
There's a school of thought that says that anything that can exist
必定存在于某些地方 如果采纳了他们的意见
must exist somewhere. And if one adopts that school of thought
那么此时我们就必须承认白洞
then at the moment we have to admit that white holes
可能在某些地方存在
might be out there somewhere.
要是大自然利用白洞的话…
If nature uses white holes...
物理学家推测那可能是宇宙最早阶段
physicists speculate that they could have been an important element
的一个重要因素
in the earliest stages of the universe.
甚至可能是宇宙本身形成的重要因素
Maybe even in the formation of the universe itself.
在企图破解某些宇宙的奥秘时
When trying to decode some of the mysteries of the universe
答案可能真的是黑与白
the answers may truly be black and white.
宇宙以大爆炸为起点
The universe began with the big bang:
一个不断膨胀的物质与能量的火球…
an expanding fireball of matter and energy...
起源于致密的丁点大的亚原子粒子
that started compressed as a tiny subatomic point
叫做"奇点"
called a "singularity."
奇点里面的引力极强
A singularity is a region where gravity is immensely strong.
大爆炸的奇点形成了整个宇宙
The big bang singularity gave rise to the entire universe,
容纳了空间 时间和所有的物质
which includes space, time, and all the matter that fills it.
白洞类似于奇点
A similar type of singularity is a white hole,
爱因斯坦万有引力理论显示的理论物体
a theoretical object that arises in Einstein's theory of gravity.
它本质上是倒过来的黑洞
It's essentially a black hole in reverse,
一个物质被喷出来的奇点
a point of singularity where matter is ejected.
因此 有些科学家怀疑
Consequently some scientists have wondered if the universe
宇宙是否就是白洞创造出来的
could have been created from a white hole.
描述整个宇宙的一个概念
One idea to describe the entire universe
就是它就是一个大的白洞
has been that it's one big white hole,
里面存在着一些原始的奇点的突出体
in which there's an emergence from some initial singularity.
那个创造性的思维众多思维中的一个
That creative thought is one amongst many
他们关心宇宙是如何萌芽的
for how the universe was seeded
是如何起源的 大爆炸是如何出现的
and how it began and how the Big Bang emerged.
思考一下吧 白洞释放出物质而不是吞下物质
Think about it. A white hole emits matter, it doesn't gobble up matter.
然而大爆炸不也是这样吗？那个小小的量子团
But isn't the Big Bang that same thing? That small little quantum dot
不也膨胀和喷出物质吗？
that expands and spews out matter?
因此也许白洞会是我们宇宙的故事
So perhaps the white hole could be the story of our universe.
美国宇航局的威尔金森各向异性探测器
NASA's Wilkinson microwave anisotropy probe
简称WMAP
known as WMAP,
已经测量了很早时期宇宙残留的辐射
has measured the radiation left over from the very early universe.
这个宇宙微波背景的研究已经证明
Studies of this cosmic microwave background have confirmed
宇宙起源于瞬间
that the universe began with a brief
但诞生时增长迅猛 称之为"膨胀"
but colossal growth birth, called "inflation",
迅猛于膨胀的正常时期
that preceded its regular phase of expansion.
所以一些科学家推测 白洞有可能
So some scientists speculate whether a white hole
是这个诞生时增长迅猛的始作俑者
could have been the instigator of this growth birth.
证据来自我们的空间卫星
The evidence coming from our space satellites
比如现在正在地球轨道上运行的WMAP
like the WMAP orbiting the Earth right now,
是和多元宇宙的概念相吻合的
is consistent with the idea of a multiverse.
多元宇宙是由许多宇宙组成的
A multiverse consists of many universes
就象肥皂泡漂浮在泡沫液里
like soap bubbles floating in a bubble bath.
在泡沫液里我们看到气泡涨起 破裂
In a bubble bath we have bubbles popping into existence, collapsing back
产生了婴儿肥皂泡 换句话说
giving birth to baby soap bubbles. So in other words
大爆炸一直没停过
Big Bangs could be happening all the time.
也许每个大爆炸都是开始于白洞
Perhaps each Big Bang starts with a
然后迅速膨胀
white hole, that then expands rapidly
带给我们一个初生的宇宙
giving us a baby universe.
有待证实 是否存在多元宇宙
It's still unproven whether multiple universes exist
比不是白洞创造了这些宇宙
and whether white holes may have created them.
但是科学家已经证明了有些类型的白洞
But scientists have shown that some types of white holes
虽然它们在理论上可能非常不稳定
although possible in theory are highly unstable.
它们生命周期不会很长
They would not survive for very long
它们很快就崩塌形成黑洞
and they simply collapse to form black holes.
也许白洞扮演了一个角色
Possibly white holes played a role, perhaps they
也许它们只形成了一个非常短的时间
formed for a very short time
然而就因为不稳定而崩塌了 甚至在这过程中
but then being unstable they collapsed. But even during that period
在它们形成的一开始
when they were first formed they may have left
就在未来的宇宙里留下了重要的烙印
some important imprint on the future of the universe.
我们不知道这些是不是真的 但却是有可能的
We don't know whether that's true, but it's a possibility.
白洞充满了不错的积极的想象 但是…
White holes are a nice active imagination, but...
我不认为它们具有任何的物质
I don't think they have any substance yet.
它们完全是理论上的东西
They're entirely theoretical objects.
但另一方面黑洞是曾经风靡一时的东西
But then black holes were that way once upon a time.
白洞有可能 也没有可能存在于宇宙的开端
White holes might or might not have existed at the beginning of the universe
但是有一个情况是确定无疑的黑洞已不再是科学幻想了
but one thing's certain: black holes are no longer science fiction.
它们是科学事实
They're science fact.
科学家们承认那些快速旋转的旋涡云
Scientists agree these whirling vortexes are born
是诞生于濒临死亡的巨大恒星
out of the death throes of massive stars.
在足够大的恒星耗尽其燃料时
When a sufficiently massive star runs out of fuel
已经无法支撑其自身来对抗它的引力作用
it is unable to support itself against its own gravitational pull.
它就向内塌落形成黑洞
It then collapses inward to form a black hole.
黑洞在宇宙演化中是个麻烦制造者
Black holes are troublemakers in the evolution of the universe.
它们把物质吸进去 把物质抛出去
They can draw matter in, spew it out
重组改造宇宙的各个地区
reform, reorganize regions of the universe,
也许是银河的某个部分
perhaps part of a galaxy,
霸占着中央 操纵着…
take up residence at the center start running the show...
它们是些强劲的大家伙
They're big muscular things
乱七八糟的东西围绕这它们运行一刻都停不下来
that lumber around and cannot be stopped.
黑洞难以察觉是因为他们很暗
Black holes are difficult to detect because they're black
但是当它们与太空中的其它物体互动时就可以观察到
but they can be observed when they interact with something in space,
比如在塌落的气体里
such as in falling gas
气体会被加热而发出X射线
which heats up and glows in X-rays.
好多年前黑洞被认为不可能的
Years ago black holes were considered to be impossible.
物理学中有个叫"可笑因子"的东西
We have something called "the giggle factor" in physics.
每当人们谈论起黑洞 大家都感到非常可笑
People used to giggle whenever we talked about black holes.
然而现在我们已经看到了数百
But now we see hundreds,
数千个黑洞的光彩现象
thousands of glorious photographs of black holes.
至少存在两类黑洞
There are at least two types of black holes.
一类叫做"恒星质量的黑洞"
One is called a "stellar mass black hole",
大约是太阳质量的3到30倍
which is approximately 3 to 30 times the mass of our Sun.
据推测有1亿个这样的黑洞
It's speculated that 100 million of these
存在于我们的银河系里
reside in our Milky Way galaxy
其它行系里也有这同样的数量
and similar numbers in other galaxies.
另一个叫做"超大质量黑洞"
The other is a "supermassive black hole",
是我们太阳质量的几百万到几十亿倍
that is millions to billions of times the mass of our Sun.
我们认为这个庞大的怪物
It's believed that this humongous monster
存在于大多数非常庞大的行系的中心
lives at the center of most every large galaxy.
我们的银河系里就有一个
Our own Milky Way galaxy has one.
然而无论它们是恒星质量规模还是超级庞大
Yet whether they're stellar mass size or super massive,
所有的黑洞都是宇宙间的吃人者
all black holes are cosmic cannibals.
黑洞某些方面象宇宙捕蟑盒
A black hole in some sense is like a cosmic roach motel.
有东西进去却没东西出来
Everything checks in but nothing checks out.
访问黑洞是荒诞的
A trip to a black hole would be fantastic,
几乎是痴人说梦
almost psychedelic.
就象是找死
It's like having a near-death experience.
如果你离黑洞很近
As you get even closer to the black hole
吸引力就将你的身体撕开
tidal forces begin to stretch your body apart
那么你的头部 屁股
so that the top of your body and the bottom of your body
体验到了不同的引力
experience different gravitational forces,
你就成了意大利面条了
and you become "spaghettified". Eventually even the atoms
最终甚至你身体中的原子都变成了面条四分五裂
of your body become noodles and become ripped apart.
至于超大质量黑洞
In the case of a supermassive black hole
意大利面条的加工过程稍微有点不同
the process of spaghettification is somewhat different.
人跳进去不会马上变成面条
The person jumping in wouldn't be spaghettified
一直要到通过了黑洞的边界
until passing through the event horizon
原因是拉伸人体的潮汐力量
and the reason for that is because the tidal forces that would stretch him
还不够强大 一直要到离奇点很近才行
aren't strong enough until you get closer to the singularity.
因此人跳进去会有片刻的感觉
So the person jumping in would have a few moments of perception
他们在黑洞里面会感到惊奇
that they were inside of a black hole and they could marvel at that idea,
随后猛然…
before they plunged
跌进奇点变成了面条
toward the singularity and then became spaghettified.
如果一个黑洞还不够残暴的话
And if one black hole isn't violent enough
那么就来试一下两个黑洞为了支配地位的决斗吧
try two black holes dueling for dominance.
在浩瀚的太空中
In the vastness of space
黑洞偶尔也会成双成对
black holes occasionally pair off.
在我看来仿佛它们在相互表现魅力
I may appear as though they're engaging
有点象宇宙间的求爱
in some sort of cosmic courtship
但是这些结合根本就不和谐
but these unions are anything but harmonious.
一旦两个黑洞靠得很近
When two black holes get too close
它们就会被相互间的引力套牢
they become trapped by each other's gravity.
这两个相互围绕这运转的黑洞就像快速旋转的托钵僧
The two orbit around each other like whirling dervishes.
这些结对的黑洞
These binary black holes
最终将碰撞合并在一起
will eventually collide and coalesce.
人们认为黑洞之间的碰撞十分普遍
It's believed that collisions between black holes would be quite common.
它们会相互围绕着运转然后向内旋转
They would be in orbit around each other and then spiral inwards
在某些时候它们会合并起来
and at some point they would coalesce
而合并会造成时空中巨大的混乱
and that coalescence creates a huge disturbance in space-time.
如果有两个扭曲四周大量空间的物体
If you have two objects that are bending space a lot around them
它们合并在一起
and they merge together
那么就会泛起涟漪波纹将释放出所携带的能量
then you'll get this ripple, this wave going out carrying energy with it.
具有代表性的是当黑洞碰撞时
Typically, when black holes collide
会产生狂野的震动 叫做"引力波"
they create wild vibrations called"gravitational waves"
它会跨越时空进行传播
which spread across the fabric of space and time.
这些涟漪就象你在池塘水面上看到涟漪
These ripples will be just like the ripples you would have say on the surface of a pond.
如果你向池塘里扔块卵石就会产生一个干扰
If you threw a pebble into a pond it creates a disturbance
接着你就会看到涟漪泛起…
and then you see the ripples carrying...
干扰到池塘的远处各点
that disturbance away to far points of the pond.
过去 结对的黑洞的碰撞很难被察觉
In the past binary black hole collisions were impossible to identify.
现在科学家们开发了引力波探测器
Now scientists have developed gravitational wave detectors
来追踪这些震动
to track these vibrations
可望捕捉到黑洞的碰撞
and hopefully catch black hole collisions in the act.
LIGO(激光干涉引力波天文台)是地面天文台
LIGO is a ground-based observatory
眼下正在进行引力波的搜索
that's currently searching for gravity waves
包括比我们的太阳质量大几倍的恒星规模的
produced from collisions involving stellar-sized black holes
黑洞碰撞所产生的引力
a few times the mass of our Sun.
这个系统利用激光
The system uses lasers
来测量靠金属线吊着的镜子的移动
to measure the motions of mirrors that hang by wires from overhead supports.
当两个黑洞合并时
When two black holes merge together
它们将释放出引力波
they'll release these gravitational waves,
就会在太空中产生涟漪
these ripples in the shape of space.
当涟漪经过这些了不起的玩艺儿时
And as the ripples pass by
就会非常细微地改变
these giant contraptions they alter ever so slightly
这些探测器之间的距离
the distances between these detectors
探测器实际上就能
and the detectors can actually...
监测到距离的变化
monitor and see that change in distance
那就是引力波前来报到了
and that's the signature of a gravitational wave coming by.
未来的LISA
In the future LISA,
由美国宇航局和欧洲航天局合作
a joint NASA and European Space Agency mission,
将能够发现超大质量黑洞碰撞造成的引力波
will be able to detect waves from collisions involving supermassive black holes.
这些两个星系合并所产生的影响
These impacts occur after two galaxies have merged
它们那超大质量黑洞就会淹没在
and their supermassive black holes sink to the center
新形成的星系中央 并且相互寻找对方
of the newly formed galaxy and find each other.
如果两个超大质量黑洞碰撞还不够混乱的话
And if collisions involving two supermassive black holes isn't chaotic enough,
那么就来看看三个
try three.
2007年1月 美国和欧洲的卫星
In January 2007 U.S. and European Satellites
居然观察到了三个
actually observed black hole triplets
它们在100亿光年外的室女座
Ten billions light-years away in the Virgo constellation.
它们实际上三个类星体
They're actually three Quasars which are luminous objects
认为是由位于星系中心的超大质量黑洞提供动力的
thought to be powered by supermassive black holes located in the centers of galaxies.
这三个互相靠近
This trio is in close proximity to one another.
它们之间只有10万到15万光年的距离
They're only about 100,000 to 150,000 light-years apart
相当于我们银河系的宽度
which is about the width of our Milky Way.
十有八九 这三个最终将进行恶意兼并
In all probability the three will eventually engage in a hostile merger.
如果你将这三个大黑洞放到靠得很近
If you take three large black holes
因为两个大的旋转即椭圆星系
brought close together because two big spiral or elliptical galaxies
已经撞在一起了 那真是一场混战了
have slammed together then it's a real free-for-all.
它们中的两个将胜出而第三个将出局
And two of them could win the game and throw the third one out.
三个物体相互之间的引力
Gravitational interactions between three bodies
会导致将其中的一个超大质量黑洞
can lead to the ejection
喷射出系统
of one of the supermassive black holes from the system
然后你就只留下了两个超大质量黑洞
and then you're just left with a binary
最终也将合并
supermassive pair that will coalesce ultimately.
被逐出的那个超大质量黑洞
The supermassive black hole that gets ejected
明显被足够的速度喷射出去
is ejected typically with enough speed
它携带不了恒星
that it can't carry stars with it
所以就变成了离群闲逛的黑洞
so it becomes a rogue black hole.
它孤芳自赏了
It's off on its own.
现代科学持续不断地破解了
Modern science continues to unravel
黑洞周围的奥秘
the mysteries surrounding black holes
但是某些问题始终未解
but for some one enduring question remains.
所有黑洞物理学中最深层的问题是
The deepest question in all of black hole physics
黑洞的对立面是什么呢？
is "what lies on the other side of a black hole?"
如果将百科全书扔进黑洞会有什么结果？
What happens if you throw the encyclopedia into a black hole?
所有的信息都会丢失吗？我们确实不知道
Is all that information lost? We don't know for sure.
根据爱因斯坦的广义相对论
According to Einstein's general relativity laws
没什么能逃脱黑洞
nothing can ever come out of a black hole.
但如果一个黑洞极其细小
But if a black hole is extremely tiny
量子力学将和广义相对论并起来了
the laws of quantum mechanics merge with the laws of general relativity.
量子力学管辖着微观世界
Quantum mechanics governs the world of the very small
比如电子 中子及其它次原子微粒
such as electrons, neutrons and other subatomic particles.
广义相对论管辖着宏观世界
General relativity rules the world of the very large
那里 受着普通的万有引力支配
where ordinary gravity is dominant
比如行星 恒星和星系
like planets, stars and galaxies.
事实上当你将量子论与黑洞放在一起
The fact is, when you put together quantum theory with black holes
你就会发现它们并不完全是
you find that they aren't completely
只吞噬不吐东西的懒惰的物体
inert objects that only suck things in and nothing comes out.
它们实际上是有射线的
They actually radiate.
有射线的黑洞称之为"迷你黑洞"
The black holes that radiate are called "mini black holes"
它们要比其恒星质量的黑洞
which are much smaller than their stellar-mass
或超大质量黑洞兄弟小很多
or supermassive black hole cousins.
著名的物理学家史蒂芬·霍金提出
Celebrated physicist Stephen Hawking proposed
如果有迷你黑洞存在它们就必定会发出辐射
that if mini black holes exist they must emit radiation
这被命名为"霍金辐射"
which has been named "Hawking radiation".
据认为这种辐射会造成微小的黑洞
It is believed this radiation will cause a tiny black hole
蒸发和潜在的消失
to evaporate and potentially disappear.
霍金给出了数学证明
Hawking gave mathematical evidence
在微小的黑洞形成然后蒸发时
that when a tiny black hole forms and then evaporates
一些信息会带进黑洞
some of the information that went into the black hole
永远回不来了
never comes back out.
这个惊人的预言给物理学家们带来了一场大灾难
This startling prediction caused a firestorm among physicists,
因为量子理论坚持
because the laws of quantum theory insist
信息决不可能完全被消灭
that information can never be completely destroyed.
基本上世界分成了两个阵营
Essentially the world split into two camps:
有些人认为霍金的预言是对的
those who believe that Hawking's calculation
而对立面则认为:"那好
was really it, and the other camp that said:"Well,
霍金的预言需要进一步地推敲"
Hawking's calculation needs refining."
弦理论和其他理论似乎暗示了
String theory and other theories seem to suggest
信息实际上是保存着
that the information is actually preserved.
只是要非常巧妙地获得
It just comes out very subtly.
进入黑洞里面的信息的结局的问题
The question of what happens to the information that goes inside a black hole is,
我认为没有完全解决
I think, not fully settled.
进入黑洞的物体的化学成分
The chemical composition of the objects that went into the black hole,
它们的其它形态 颜色 温度等等
the other aspects of them, their color, their temperature, et cetera et cetera.
我们真的不知道那些信息的结局
We don't really know what happens to that information.
看来不大可能
It appears unlikely
科学家们会冒险进入任何一个黑洞
that scientists could venture inside any black hole
取出一块带回家来报告他们的调查结果
and return back home in one piece, to report their findings.
然而科学家的全球合作
But a worldwide collaboration of scientists
可能处于下一个最大的事情的边缘:
may be on the verge of the next best thing:
制造出微小的黑洞 就在地球上!
manufacturing tiny black holes, right here on Earth.
如今科学家们退回到了宇宙研究的分界线
Today, scientists are pushing back the boundaries of cosmic research.
如果自然形成的黑洞不够可怕的话
If naturally formed black holes aren't scary enough,
那么黑洞工厂又有什么呢？
what about a black hole factory?
在瑞士的CERN物理实验室(欧洲粒子物理实验室)
In Switzerland, at the physics laboratory called CERN,
科学家已经建起了大型强子对撞机
scientists have built the Large Hadron Collider
最大 最复杂 以前从来没有过的科学实验
the biggest, most complex, science experiment ever constructed.
这是一种粒子加速器
It's a particle accelerator,
十七英里长 5架大型喷气式客机的重量
17 miles long and the weight of five jumbo jets.
它能够将次原子粒子挤压在一起
It's capable of crushing subatomic particles together
复制大爆炸后百万分之几秒里的能量
to replicate the energies that existed microseconds after the Big Bang.
设计和建造这个粒子对撞机
This particle collider was designed and built
是为了研究基本粒子物理学中的重要课题
to study important questions in fundamental particle physics.
然而它将这么多的能量硬挤在一起
But it will cram so much energy together
如果物理学家侥幸碰到那些能量的自然运作
that if physicists are lucky about how nature works at those energies,
那也就能产生微小的黑洞了
it could also produce tiny black holes.
我们认为能够看到微观黑洞
We might be able to see microscopic black holes being formed
正在这些高能碰撞中形成
in these high energy collisions and
那些黑洞接着就能够得到研究
those black holes would then be amenable to study.
它们会迅速蒸发
They would rapidly evaporate.
我们将能够研究它们的衰变产物
We'll be able to study their decay products, and understand
在实验室里了解量子引力的物理性质
physics of quantum gravity in the laboratory,
这是我们有生之年永远的梦想追求的东西
which is something that we never dreamed to be able to do in our lifetimes.
然而制造迷你黑洞的可能性
But the possibility of manufacturing mini black holes
已经引起了怀疑和恐惧
has roused suspicion and fear.
它们会摆脱地球引力
Could they escape the Earth's gravity
最终吞噬我们地球吗？
and eventually devour our planet?
来自外层空间的宇宙射线一直在轰击地球
Cosmic rays from outer space hit the Earth all the time
也许要比这些迷你黑洞的能量更大
perhaps with more energy than these mini black holes.
所以这些迷你黑洞是无害的
So these mini black holes are harmless.
它们不会吃掉地球的 它们不是世界末日的设备
They're not gonna eat up the Earth. They are not a doomsday device.
类似的迷你黑洞恐惧 在美国也发生过
A similar mini black hole scare, happened in the United States.
在纽约的布鲁克海文
In Brookhaven, New York
较小的对撞实验早在进行了
a smaller collider experiment is already underway.
相对论重离子对撞机 简称RHIC
The Relativistic Heavy Ion Collider, better known as RHIC,
是一个地下管线
is an underground pipeline
黄金原子在里面对撞
where gold atoms collide together
其速度达到光速的99.9%
at 99.9 percent the speed of light.
2000年实验开始时
When the experiment began, in the year 2000,
消息传出那些迎面相撞将制造出黑洞
news spread that these head-on impacts created black holes.
实验室非常负责任 决定作出回应让人们放心
The laboratory, which is very responsible, decided that it need to respond to this and
因此召集了一帮人来进行评判
reassure people. So it convened a group to look at this
那帮人发现
and what that group found was
这些碰撞早已在外太空发生了…
that these kinds of collisions had been happening in outer space and...
从来没有造成任何问题从理论上说…
that had never caused a problem. Theoretically...
我们是在这些碰撞中创造条件
we produce conditions, in these collisions, which should
这些条件是数学给出的理论上的黑洞周围的一些类似条件
mathematically give some similarity to the theory that surrounds black holes,
但实际上我们完全是安全的
but in practice, we're completely safe.
根本不用担心在RHIC会制造出任何黑洞
There's no way that any black hole that could be a concern could be produced here at RHIC.
是的 RHIC确实没有能力
Well, RHIC certainly is not capable
做出任何一种黑洞
of producing a black hole of any kind.
这里通过多个数量级创造不出足够的质量
There is not enough mass which is being created here by many orders of magnitude.
尽管RHIC不可能制造出迷你黑洞
Although RHIC cannot create mini black holes,
但科学家可以通过这些粒子碰撞的灰烬
scientists can go through the ashes of these particle collisions
来研究那早期时刻
to learn about the early moments:
大爆炸后的百万分之几秒
a few microseconds after the Big Bang.
因此我们能够利用这个知识
So we can use this knowledge
以便更好地了解
to gain a better understanding
大爆炸后所不久发生的情况
of what happened shortly after the Big Bang,
包括原始黑洞形成的可能性
including the possibility of...primordial black hole formation.
瑞士和美国的粒子碰撞实验
The particle collision experiments in Switzerland and in the U.S.
不可能产生危及生命的黑洞
may not produce life-threatening black holes...
然而它们提供了几个重要的线索
but they could give several important clues
那是关于信息能否从迷你黑洞里返回
about whether information comes back out of the mini black hole,
甚至宇宙是如何诞生的
and even how the universe began.
他们装备了一个实验室
They do provide a laboratory
来观察我们能将爱因斯坦的理论推进多远
to see how far we can push Einstein's theory
直到所有的枷锁解脱 平衡倒塌
until all hell breaks loose, and the equations collapse.
这就是为什么我们认为迷你黑洞
And that's why we think that mini black holes
可能是超越爱因斯坦的关键
could be a key to going beyond Einstein.
物理学家将继续深入探究
Physicists will continue to probe into the mysteries
这个沉寂在黑洞周围的奥秘
still surrounding black holes.
他们也将继续对难以捉摸的虫洞和白洞
They will also remain on high alert
的任何迹象保持高度的关注
for any signs of the elusive wormholes and white holes.
对下一个领域的探索继续在推进
The search for the next frontier marches on.
白洞 虫洞 黑洞
White holes, wormholes, black holes are...
是多半会被遗忘的门票
tickets to oblivion for the most part.
它们没有一个是你想在暑假去的地方
None of these are places that you wanna take your summer vacation near,
这些门票要找到 代价很高
and these tickets will cost a lot to even find.
这些物体在宇宙中很难被观察到
These objects are hard to observe in the universe and...
只有其中的一个 我们已经差不多了解了 它就是:黑洞
only one of them do we really pretty much know is there: the black hole.
其它的可能完全是假设
The others may be entirely hypothetical.
它们可能是天文学上的独角兽
They may be the unicorns of astronomy.
科学史上有几个案例
There are several cases in the history of science when
一个想法乃至解决一个方程式
an idea or even a solution to an equation
就似乎是我们想象力的一个手工艺品
just seems like an artifact of our imaginations
实际上结果是真实的东西
and actually turned out to be a real thing.
黑洞就是这样的一个例子
Black holes are such an example.
也许白洞和虫洞实际上也具有某些作用
Maybe white holes and wormholes will have some role in nature
有朝一日我们会发现
which we'll one day discover.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing